A Guide to the Papers of James Langstaff Dunn, 1850-1906, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Langstaff Dunn, 1850-1906, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8301, -a, -b
This collection consists of ca. 150 items in one box.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the library by Josephine Shamburg Johnston, of Charlottesville, VA, on February 15, 1988.
Provenance
This collection descended to Josephine Shamburg Johston, the granddaughter of Dr. Dunn.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dunn was born near Meadville, Crawford County, Pa. on September 9, 1826. He married Temperance Osborne at Hayfield, Crawford County, on October 15, 1849. The couple had four children -- Josephine A., James A., Jessie, and Gertrude.
Dunn enlisted in the Union Army from Crawford County, Pa., on April 16, 1861, as a Captain of Company D., Erie Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry. He did not continue with the Company, however, as he was appointed Surgeon of Pennsylvania Volunteers with the rank of Major. For three years, he was Surgeon of the 109th Regiment. During service, he participated in engagements at Cedar or Slaughter Mountain, Va.; 2nd Bull Run, South Mountain, Antietam, Md.; Chancellorsville, VA.; Gettysburg, Pa.; Wauhatchie, Chattanooga, Lookout Mountain and Mission Ridge, Tenn. His 12th Corps was consolidated with the 20th Corps, Army of the Potoma, which was engaged at Ringgold, Ga.; and other areas in Goergia including Mill Creek Gap, Peach Tree Creek, Resaca, Dallas or New Hope Church, Kenesaw Mountain, Pine Knob, Culpie Farm, Muddy Creek, and others and the Siege of Atlanta and March to the Sea at Savannah.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of letters from James Langstaff Dunn, a Brigade Surgeon to the 2nd Brigade, Banks Corp, 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division, 12th and 20th Army Corps, to his wife (with a few exceptions). It also includes a portfolio of his personal military and civil history.
Dunn's letters are chiefly filled with news of family and friends. He describes camp life, food, marches, weather, illnesses among the troops, battles, treatment of the wounded, and his thoughts on the war. There is a gap in the letters between January and April, 1864, when Dunn was apparently at home on leave for several months.
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 16, 1850. (Folder 1.)
    Sent from James in Cleveland to his wife in Saegertown, Crawford County, Pa., about his homesickness.
  - Alfred [Osborne] to Temperance Dunn. December 7, 1850. (Folder 1.)
    Sent to Temperance from her brother Alfred discussing family matters.
  - Alfred [Osborne] to Temperance Dunn. April 27, 1854. (Folder 1.)
    Sent to Temperance from her brother Alfred discussing some philosophical views.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 20, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    From Camp Wilkins, he tells his wife about activities of many Crawford County friends he has encountered.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 29, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    From Camp Wilkins, Pa., he writes of his company being ordered to the Virginia line where an attack is expected on Uniontown in Fayette County and warns that he expects to smell "powder" in less than ten days; mentions that provisions are being cooked and swords sharpened--all in good spirits.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 2, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    He says his orders to move have been countermanded, instead he travels to Harrisburg and visits Camp Curtain, writing "as a general thing, the men look green and young...I could easily tell why General McCall pronounced us as 'the best body of troops he ever saw;" says he saw the surgeon's examinations which are very strict and severe.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 5, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    From Philadelphia, he asks Temperance how the Bates' baby "got along with that lump I cut out--did it get well or not?"
  - ? Barnes, Camp Benelly, to Captain J. L. Dunn. September 17, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    Informs Dunn he is having his wife send the sword to Eaton, discusses Colonel Maclane and the regiment in Washington, and congratulates Dunn on his recent appointment.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 6, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    Dunn writes he has left Col. McLane's (John W.) Regiment on the Potomac and has been assigned as a surgeon in Philadelphia--describes McLane as a "sneak and a double-dealing villain."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 12, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    Describes for his wife how he passes his time. He boards at a private house for $3 a week; among other things, he examines new recruits, attends lectures at the Jefferson Medical College, and attends private anatomy instruction.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 24, 1861. (Folder 2.)
    Tells his wife he won't be home by New Year's, but may be returning home in another 2-3 weeks. He must first get his "subject" dissected before he leaves. Asks wife to send money for his board.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 2, [1862]. (Folder 3.)
    Gives vivid description of the city during the Christmas holidays--crowds, parks, theaters, etc.
  - James Dunn to Master Fredy Dunn (his son). January 12, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Describes "poor little boys that I see everyday by the streets trying to make a living by blacking boots."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 12, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Writes he is busy examining recruits and must be careful not to accept "defective men" as if get in service and are found unsound he is responsible for expense of transportation and discharge; describes in detail his daily life at the hospital--attending lectures, dissecting and operating on the dead, and meeting for discussion with surgeons of different regiments--some of them the "first medical men of America."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. February 10, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Relieved to hear that Freddy is recovered; Dunn had been about to start for home the next day when he heard the news. Discusses expensive living in Philadelphia, and encourages her to visit him when Freddy was better. Included a small note for Freddy to get well and "come see this great city."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 27, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    The regiment has gone into camp about ten miles from Philadelphia but he remains in the city as the assistant surgeon is in the camp.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 30, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Temperance had complained that Dunn was not writing. Mentions the things he sent home for her, especially a dress whose material "is all the fashion." The regiment was in the camp, but he remained in the Mustering office. He discusses of the slow nature of recruiting work. A friend had promised him a good revolver, and Dunn urges wife to get it to send to him.
  - James Dunn to Master Fred Dunn. April 7, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Encloses some Rebel money that he bought for 5 cents each but tells him little boys are making money selling it for 10 cents each.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 8, 1682. (Folder 3.)
    Says regiment is leaving the camp next day for Washington D.C. and then on to Manassas Junction.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 12, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    From Camp Wood near Washington--describes illness in the new camp and comments that with Merrimac blown out of water thinks war will be over soon, gives views on damage Merrimac could have done to Union's wooden boats.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 5, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    From Aspendale near Winchester-reports that after two days and two nights of hard marching from Harper's Ferry in pouring rain, the regiment has arrived near Winchester; says little damage appears in the rural countryside, despite the fact that "large armies have passed and repassed--fought and retreated."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 18, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    Writes from Headquarters of the 71st Brigade, Sigel's (Gen. Franz) Division near Strasburg, Va.--has arrived after a day's march from Kernstown; describes process involved in taking over an old Southern mansion as headquarters, with the General taking over a large bedroom and parlor as headquarters; gives poetic description of the beautiful Virginia countryside, and asks that women at home consider rolling bandages and sending them as medical supplies for the upcoming engagements; gives description of General Sigel and tells of strength of two brigades encamped there; in a frank statement remarks on the status of young black children in the area; gives position of the camp as being twenty-two miles from Jackson's army with General Fremont (John Charles) in between the two armies.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 30, 1862. (Folder 3.)
    From Headquarters of the Brigade--learns General Fremont has been replaced by General Pope; thinks General Fremont not really suited for the army, but, in some detail, expresses his opinions about his sound character; details growth in number of troops (expected to reach 125,000 men); devotes an entire page to a discussion of slaves who flee the advance of the army, the Union army as a tool of abolition, and conflicting ideas concerning slavery and the role of the slaves once they have been freed.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 12, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Headquarters, Cooper's (Gen. James) Division, tells of leaving Cedar Creek in the Valley of Virginia and marching to Front Royal, then to Sperryville, and on to three miles from Warrenton. He describes the beauty of the mountains and the rich fields along the way; once again is situated in headquarters in an old mansion; remarks with vigor and at length on the qualities of Southern aristocracy, its landowners, treatment of slaves and "poor white trash;" tells of strength of the encampment--"regiments passing night and day," hundreds of cannon and woods full of cavalry.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 26, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Camp Pleasant Valley, Washington, Va.,--says he has left Warrenton for Culpeper with Gordonsville as destination--his brigade is stopping temporarily (because of rain) at Washington, Va.; had to take the food of inhabitants, leaving them, he fears, to starve; further discussion on evils of slavery and on attitudes of southerners he has encountered in the area.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 11, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Culpeper Court House--describes the battle of Slaughter Mountain [Cedar Mountain] in detail, including the activities of surgeons (some of whom were cowardly) in healing the dead and wounded (with poignant descriptions of cries of the wounded); thinks battle could have been won if McDowell's troops (within three miles of the action) had come to aid but says McDowell is a "traitor and a jackass." tells of healing the wounds of Generals Auger (Christopher Colon) and Banks (Nathaniel Prentiss).
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 15, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Washington, D.C. This letter includes touching accounts of amputations and operations following the battle on Slaughter Mountain, and a heart-rending description of a soldier, stripped of his clothing, left for dead three days before being found alive; describes his own condition-working for twenty-four hours non-stop, no food or drink, sleeves rolled up and covered with blood; discusses the treatment of the enemy wounded.
  - Cyrus E. Buckland to Major J. L. Dunn. August 22, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    Cyrus E. Buckland of Springfield, Mass., thanks him for his communication to the widow of a deceased soldier he had treated and complimenting him on the ministrations made during the last hours of the ill and wounded.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 6, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From National Hotel, Washington, D.C., where he writes of engagements in Rappahannock and Bull Run. "No one can imagine the horrors of a battlefield;" describes his activities in the field at Bull Run-dressing the wounds of over 4,000 and giving them warm soup and tea; mentions that he is going on to Alexandria and expects to go from there to Harper's Ferry; comments on the necessity of having more dedicated recruits, not just a lot of "cowardly volunteers."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 14, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Frederick, Md., where they have just arrived, he writes a quick line to let her know he is well. Their corps drove out the enemy the day before and expects orders any moment to join the action. Dunn hopes orders will be deferred until he gets his dinner. Describes men, women, and children rushing the streets to hug and kiss the soldiers as they enter the city.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 1, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Harper's Ferry, gives detailed and realistic description of battle at Harper's Ferry and his part in it, as well as excellent appearance and condition of Rebel troops, saying--"this gray dirty dress is to their advantage for they are not as good marks as our bright blue uniforms are;" comments in depth on lack of endurance of Union generals to follow up on battlefield, talks of difficulties of keeping good horses for himself.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 8, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Harper's Ferry, he writes concerning family matters.
  - C. E. Buckland to Maj. J. L. Dunn, Brigade Surgeon. December 16, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    Writing from Buckland, Springfield, Mass., Buckland thanks Dunn for his attention at the death of his sister's husband.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. December 21, 1862. (Folder 4.)
    From Camp near Fairfax, Va.--reports on his return to this camp from Harper's Ferry, where he thinks he may stay all week; thinks "greatest problem" comes from General Halleck trying to run the war without himself being in the field; says would not be surprised if the army took control of the nation away from the people and established a military government and explains why.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 22, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Dumfries, he describes Dumfries as "hardly fit for a pig pen, relates an incident in which he swore at a Colonel and was placed under arrest for two weeks, says he has friendly relations with the men and generals with whom he serves.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. January 27, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From headquarters, 2nd division, 2nd brigade--Stafford County, Va., he describes horrible weather conditions; hears rumor that Burnside has resigned and General Joseph Hooker is in charge of army; is in favor of army taking the power away from the people for awhile; proceeds with long discussion of "traitors coming into power under the fake name of Democrats" and expresses opinions about "craven cowards" of the north who want peace when there is no peace.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. February 2, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, he writes that it is very cold, but new camp near the river is pleasant.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 11, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, Va, Head Quarters 3rd Brigade. Writes that for the past two weeks he has expected her letter and is anxious for news from home, especially concerning Freddy's cough, and mentions that he sent Freddy a good suit of clothes. Dunn writes he is happy to be surrounded by a loyal and patriotic class of men and speaks passionately against those "poor miserable wretches whose whole soul is wrapped up in the miserable doctrine of human bondage and in unison with Jeff[erson] Davis." Although he confesses a respect for the Southerners as a brave enemy, Dunn despises the "vile reptiles of sympathizers at home who are giving aid and comfort to the rebels" and speaks of himself as the enemy of all traitors.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 15, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, he writes it is snowing and raining, and he expects rebellion can be wiped out in the coming year because of the conscription act.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 21, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    Writes to her concerning family matters, including sending her money with which she can pay her father all that is due him.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. March 29, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, he rants against Copperheads; says all Pennsylvania regiments are put together in divisions with General Kane (Thomas Leiper) in command, and he is transferred to his staff.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 12, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek--describes General Kane as "very much of a gentleman" but with wounds in leg and face; gives account of first wounded soldier he treated at Cedar Mountain and tells of his vivid recollections of the occasion.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 18, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, he writes that they are ready to march at a moment's notice, anticipates a fight.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. April 21, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Aquia Creek, Dunn is disturbed by his wife's reports on son Freddie's illness; reports hearing of an increase in Washington of "houses of ill fame" to about 400 from 30 or 40 before the war, with probably ten thousand women "plying their trade."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 17, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    He tells of the loss of many friends in the battle of Chancellorsville; May 18, 1863--wants wife to come to visit.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. May 26, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    He urges wife to come to visit, to be accompanied by Lieut. Saeger of Saegertown, who is going home on leave.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. June 25, 1863. (Folder 5.)
    From Headquarters 2nd Division, 2nd Brigade, Leesburg, Va., he comments that it has been a week since wife's visit, and they are expecting a battle any hour.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 5, l863. (Folder 6.)
    From the Field Hospital, Gettysburg, Pa., he writes "have just passed through a fearful battle--we whipped the Rebels and they are in full retreat out of the state;" says he is ashamed of many Pennsylvanians who do not lift a hand to defend their homes but slink away out of sight; reports that women thereabouts charge 50 cents for a loaf of bread; rants against the "Copperheads."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 13, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Fair Plain, four miles from Antietam, he mentions hard marching since "one of the great battles of the age, and have followed the enemy up to this point;" describes the good attitude of the troops, but continues to rail against the Pennsylvanians from the lower part of the state for their "nonchalant" attitude toward the war; continues to protest against the Copperheads.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. July 18, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Headquarters, 2nd Brigade, Harper's Ferry, he laments the escape of General Lee and troops; thinks days of the Copperheads may be numbered; expects troops to leave the next morning in pursuit of Lee.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 2, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ellis Ford, Va.--mentions a cavalry battle near Culpeper the day before in very hot weather; thinks York, Pa., has brought everlasting disgrace on the State by going out 12 miles to meet the enemy and surrendering the town; thinks women of the town are humane and loyal but the men are "cowardly skunks."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 14, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ellis Ford - he mentions he has drawn three months pay and sends $400 for her to use as she sees proper, keeping $92 for himself to cover his expenses through his next pay day. Tells his wife he has quit smoking, he has not smoked a cigar or pipe for over one month.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 23, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ellis Ford, he discusses the draft and 20,000 men from picked corps sent to New York to be ready if rioting occurs--more discussion of Copperheads.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. August 29, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ellis Ford, he tells how people in that part of the country have to be fed by Union commissaries to keep them from starving, "but with all their destitution they are Secesh like the devil;" discusses desertion.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 2, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ellis Ford, he mentions some talk of being sent to Texas.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 11, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From camp near Ellis Ford, he describes workings of the Sutlership of the 109th Regiment in which he invested and has made a profit; discusses the disloyal traitors in Pennsylvania.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 17, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From camp on Raccoon Ford, Rapid Ann River, 6 miles from Cedar Mountain--in new location having driven enemy over the river.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. September 20, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From camp near Culpeper, Va., he talks about upcoming election in Pennsylvania and his desire to vote; is worried about Copperheads and discusses gallant conduct of Crawford and Erie boys and their mark on the battlefield singing "We'll rally round the flag, boys, rally once again."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 7, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Nashville, Tenn.--(his brigade transferred) he writes that they traveled by boat to Louisville and then drove to Nashville and will go on to Murfreesboro where the troops are; enemy harassing, but intend to strengthen their position and have many changes from those they had in the Army of the Potomac.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 18, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Nashville, Brigade is at Christiana 10 miles from Murfreesboro, Dunn describes the beauty of the countryside--people clever with none of that "humbug vanity of the Virginians. I have not seen a man or woman here say a word about their ancestors as being of noble descent and all that nonsense, but plain rough and ready, good-hearted people;" describes housing and the importance of having a good chimney; tells of an amusing encounter with two "Secesh."
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 23, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Stevenson, Alabama "like all the rest of Southern towns--a poor miserable hole" he describes passing over the Cumberland Mountains and through tunnels; saw Generals Grant (Ullyses S.) and Rosecrans (William Starke).
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. October 31, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Field Hospital at camp on Lookout Mountain, Dunn vividly describes battle at Wauhatchie on Lookout Mountain--a night engagement--and the many injuries there--also the death of General Geary's son (John White Geary).
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 5, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Wauhatchie, Tenn., he say they are fortified on Racoon Mountain, and ready to give the rebels "hail Columbia" if they come on. Also says General Green (George Sears) was hit in the face at Wauhatchie.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 20, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Wauhatchie, writes that he is aware of something afoot as everything is on the move; Sherman (Gen. William Tecumseh)'s forces of 30 thousand men have arrived; discusses the primitive nature of surrounding countryside; describes the dress of men and women and tobacco and snuff habits.
  - James Dunn to Temperance Dunn. November 29, 1863. (Folder 6.)
    From Ringold, Ga., he tells in detail of activities of the last week, including storming in "splendid style" of Lookout Mountain and the battle on Missionary Ridge; describes amputating leg of Capt. Greene, son of General Greene (George Sears); details many deaths and injuries--reports that "the grandest spectacle of this war and one of the most gallant on record was the charge and capture of Lookout Mountain."